okay when the camera says we'll start
you want to give me a
signal okay this is lecture eight in
linear algebra and this is the lecture
where we completely solve linear
equations so ax equal
B that's our
goal if it has a
solution it certainly can happen that
there is no solution we have to identify
that possibility by
elimination and then if there is a
solution we want to find out is there
only one solution or are is there a
whole family of solutions and then find
them all
okay can I use as an
example the same Matrix that I
had last time when we were looking for
the null space so so th the Matrix has
rows one two two 2 2 4 6 8 and the third
row you remember the main point was the
third row
368 10 is the sum of Row one plus row
two in other words if I add those
leftand sides I get the third leftand
side so you can tell me right away what
elimination is going to discover about
the right hand sides what's there is a
condition on B1 B2 and B3 for the system
to have a solution most
cases if I took these numbers to be 1
five and 17 there would not be a
solution in fact if I took those first
numbers to be one and
five what is the only B3 that would be
okay
six if the left hand if if these leftand
sides add up to that then B I need B1
plus B2 to equal
B3 let's let's just see how elimination
discovers that but but we can see it
coming right uh that that if if let me
say it in other words if some
combination on the left hand side gives
all
zeros then the same combination on the
right hand side must give zero okay so
let's
uh let me take that example and write
down instead of copying out all the plus
signs let me write down the Matrix 1 2 2
2 2 4
68 and that 63 810 were the third row is
the sum of the first two rows now how do
we deal with the right hand side that's
we we want to do the same thing to the
right hand side that we're doing to
these rows on the left side so we just
tack on the right hand side as another
Vector another column so this is the
augmented
matrix it's
it's the Matrix a with the vector B
tacked on in mat lab that's all you
would need to type okay so we do
elimination on that can we just do
elimination quickly the first pivot is
fine I subtract two of this away from
this three of this away from this so I
have one 2 2 2
B1 two of those away will give me 0
0 2 and four 4 and that was B2 minus 2
B1 I I have to do the same thing to that
third that last column and then three of
these away from this Gave Me 0 0
24 B3 minus 3
b1s so that's the that's elimination
with the First
Column
completed we move on there's the first
pivot still here's here's the second
pivot we're always remembering now these
are then going to be the pivot
columns and let
me get the final result well let me can
I can I uh do it by
eraser we're capable of
subtracting this Row from this row just
by that'll knock this out completely and
give me the row of zeros and on the
right hand side when I subtract this
away from
this what do I
have I think I have
B3 minus a B2 and I had minus three b1s
this is going to it's going to be a
minus a B1 oh yeah that's exactly what I
expect
so now what's the last
equation the last equation this
represented by this zero row that last
equation is says 0 equals B3 - B2 -
B1 so that's the condition for
solvability that's the condition on the
right hand side that we expected it says
that B1 plus B2 has to match B3 and if
our numbers happen to have been 15 and
six so let me take suppose B is
156 that's an okay B and when I do this
elimination what will I have the B1 will
still be a one B2 would be 5 - 2 this
would be a
three five 6 - 5 - one this will be this
is the main point this will be a zero
thanks okay so the last equation is okay
now and I can proceed to solve the two
equations that are really there with
four unknowns okay I I I want to do that
so this this B is okay it allows a
solution we're going to
be naturally interested to keep track
what are the conditions on B that that
uh are that that make the equation
solvable so let me put it let let me
write down what we already see before I
continue to solve it let me first
solvability
solvability so which so this is the
condition on the right hand
sides and what is that condition this is
solvability always of ax equal B so axal
B is
solvable well actually we had an
answer in the language of the column
space can you remind me what that answer
is that that was like our answer from
earlier
lecture B had to be in the column space
solvable if when exactly
when B is
in the column space of
a right that just says that B has to be
a combination of the columns and of
course that's exactly what the
equation is looking for so that that now
I want to answer it the same answer but
in different
language
another way to answer
this
if if some if a
combination of the rows of
a gives
the zero
row
if a and this was an example where it
happened some combination of the rows of
a produced the zero row then what's the
requirement on
B that's since we're going to do the
same thing to both sides of all
equations the same
combination of the components of B has
to give zero right that's so if there's
a combination of the rows that gives the
zero row then the
same
combination of the entries of
B must give
zero and this isn't the zero row that's
the zero
number okay that this is another way of
saying and it's it's not immediate right
that these two statements
are
equivalent but somehow they must be
because they're both equivalent to the
solvability of the system
Okay so we've got this this sort of like
question zero is does the system have a
solution okay I'll come back to discuss
that
further let's go
forward when it does when there is a
solution and so what's our job now
abstractly we sit back and we say okay
there's a solution finished it exists
but we want to construct it so what's
the
algorithm the the the sequence of steps
to find the solution that's what I and
and of course the quiz and the final I'm
going to give you a system ax equal B
and I'm going to ask you for the
solution if there is one and so it's
this algorithm that you want
to
follow
okay let's
see so what's the so now to
find the complete
solution to axal
B okay let me start by finding one
solution one particular
solution I'm expecting that I can
because my system of equations now that
last equation is 0 equals
z so that's all fine I really have two
equations actually I've got four
unknowns so I'm expecting to find not
only a solution but a whole bunch of
them but let's just find one so step
one a particular solution X
particular how do I find one particular
solution well let me tell you how how I
how I find it there so this is since
since there are lots of solutions you
could have your own way to find a
particular one but this is a pretty
Natural Way
set all free varibles
to
zero since those free variables are the
guys that can be
anything the most convenient choice is
zero and then
solve axal B for the pivot
variables so what does that mean in this
example which are the free variables
which which are the variables that we
can assign freely and then and then
there's one and only one way to find the
pivot variables they're X2 and so X2 is
zero because that's in a column without
a pivot the second column has no pivot
and the what's the other one the fourth
X4 is zero because that's those are the
the free
ones those are in the columns with no
pivots so do you see what my so when I
knock when X2 and X4 are
zero I'm left with
the what am I left with here I'm just
left with see now I'm not using the two
free columns I'm only using the pivot
columns so I'm really left with X1 the
first equation is just X1 and 2 x3s
should be the right hand side which we
picked to be a one and the second
equation is 2
x3s as it happened turned out to be uh
three
I I just write it again here with the X2
and the X4 knocked out since we set them
to zero and you see that we we're back
in the normal case of having back we're
back substitution will do it so
X3 is three halves and then we go back
up and X1 is 1 - 2x3 that's probably
min-2 good so now we have the solution X
particular is the vector minus 2 0 three
Hales
zero okay good that's one particular
solution and we should and could plug it
into the original system really if on
the quiz please it's a good thing to do
just so we did all this these row
operations but this is supposed to solve
the original system and I think it does
okay so that's X
particular which we've got
so that's like what's new
today the particular solution comes
first you check that you have 0 equals z
so you're okay on the last
equations and then you set the free
variables to zero solve for the pivot
variables and you've got a particular
solution the particular solution that
has zero free variables okay now but
that's only one solution and now I'm
looking for
all so how do I find the rest the point
is I can add on
two add on X anything out of the null
space
we know how to find the vectors in the
null space because we did it last time
but I'll REM remind you what we got and
then I'll
add so the final result will be that the
complete solution this is now the
complete guy the complete solution is
this one particular solution Plus any
any
Vector all different vectors out of the
null
space xn okay why why this pattern
because this pattern shows up through
all of mathematics because it shows up
everywhere we have linear equations let
me just put here the the reasoning
a
XP so that's X particular so what does a
x particular give that gives the correct
right hand side
B and what does a times an X in the null
space
give zero so I
add and I put in parentheses so XP +
xn is B+ 0 which is B so oh what am I
saying let me just say it in words
if I have one
solution one solution I can add on
anything in the null space because
anything in the null space has a zero
right hand side and and I still have the
correct right hand side B so that's my
system that's my complete solution now
let me write out what that will be for
this example so so this example in this
example expert X General X
complete the complete solution is X
particular which is -2 0 32 0 with those
zeros in the free variable plus you
remember there were the special
Solutions in the null space that had a
one in the free variables or or one and
zero in the free variables and then we
filled in to find the others I've
forgotten what they were but maybe it
was that that was a special solution and
then there was another special solution
that had that free variable zero and
this free variable equal one and I have
to fill those
in let's see can I remember how those
fill in maybe this was a minus two and
this was a two
possibly I think probably that's
right I'm not yeah
to H does that look right to you I would
have to remember what are my equations
can can I rather than go way back to
that board let me remember the first
equation was
2x3 + 2x4 equaling zero now because I'm
looking for the guys in the null space
so I said X4 to be
one and the second equation that I
didn't copy again gave me minus two for
this and then yeah so I think that's
right 2 - 4 and two gives zero
check okay those were the special
Solutions what do we do to get the
complete
solution how do I get the complete
solution now I multiply this by
anything C1 say and I multiply this by
anything I take any combination remember
that's how we described the null space
the null space consists of all
combinations of so this is
xn all combinations of the special
Solutions there were two special
Solutions because there were two free
variables and we want to make that count
uh com carefully now but just while I'm
up here so there's that's what the
that's the kind of answer I'm looking
for is there a constant multiplying this
guy is there a free constant that
multiplies X particular no way right X
particular solves a XP equal B I'm not
allowed to multiply that by three but
AXN I'm allowed to multiply xn by three
or add to another xn because I keep
getting zero on the right okay so so
again
XP is one particular guy xn is a whole
Subspace right it's one guy plus plus
anything from a
Subspace let me draw it let me let me
try to
oh I want to draw I want to graph all
this graph I want to I want to
plot all
solutions
now X so what dimension am I
in this is an unfortunate
Point how many components does X have
four there are four unknown so I have to
draw a
four-dimensional picture on this MIT
cheap Blackboard okay so uh here we go
X1 uh Einstein could do it but uh this
this is th those are are
four
perpendicular
axes in representing four-dimensional
space
okay where are my Solutions do my
solutions form a
Subspace do does the set of solutions to
ax equal B form a Subspace no way what
does it actually look like though there
a Subspace is in this picture this part
is a Subspace
right that part is some like
two-dimensional because I've got two
parameters so it's I'm thinking of this
null space as a two-dimensional Subspace
inside
R4 now I have to tell you and we'll tell
you next time what does it mean to say a
Subspace what's the dimension of a
Subspace but you see what it's going to
be it's the number
of free independent constants that we
can choose so somehow there'll be a
two-dimensional Subspace not a line and
not a three-dimensional plane but only a
two-dimensional guy but it's doesn't go
through the origin because it goes
through this point so there's X
particular X particular is somewhere
here x particular so it's somehow a
Subspace can I try to draw it that
way it's a two-dimensional Subspace that
goes through X
particular and then onwards by so
there's X particular and I added on xn
and there's X there's xal XP +
xn but the xn was anywhere in the
Subspace so that filled
out a plane it's it's a it's a Subspace
it's not a Subspace what am I saying
it's it's it's like a flat thing it's
like a Subspace but it's been shifted uh
away from the origin it doesn't contain
zero okay thanks that's the picture and
that's the
algorithm so the algorithm is just go
through
elimination and uh find the particular
solution and then find those special
Solutions you you can do that
that let me take our time here in the
lecture to
think uh about the bigger
picture so let me think
about uh so this this is my pattern now
I want to think I want to ask
you about a question I want to ask you
some
questions so when I mean think big I
mean I'll think about an M by n
Matrix
a of rank
R
okay what's our definition of rank our
current definition of rank is number of
pivots okay first of all how are these
numbers related can you tell me a
relation between R and
M if I have M rows in The Matrix and R
pivots then I certainly
know I know
always what what relation do I know
between r and
m r is less or equal right because I've
got M rows I can't have more than M
pivots I might have M and I might have
fewer also I've got n columns so what's
the relation between R and N it's the
same less or equal
because a column can't have more than
one
pivot so I can't have more than n pivots
all together okay okay so I have an M
byn Matrix of rank
R and I always know R less than or equal
m r less or equal n now I'm specially
interested in the case of full rank when
the rank R is as big as it can be
well I guess I've got two separate
possibilities
here depending on what these numbers M
and N are so let me talk about the case
of
full column
Rank and by that I mean
means r equal
n and I want to ask you
what's what does that imply about
our Solutions what does that tell us
about the null
space what does that tell us about uh
the the complete solution okay so what
does that mean so I I want to ask you
what
okay if the rank is
n what does that mean that means there's
a pivot in every
column so how many pivot variables are
there n all the columns have pivots in
this case so how many free variables are
there none at
all so no free variables r equal n no
free
variables so what does that tell us
about what's going to happen then in our
in our little algorithms What will what
will be in the null
space the null space of
a has got what in
it only the zero Vector there are no
free variables to give other values
to so the null space is only the zero
vector
and what about our solution to ax equal
B
solution to ax equal B what what's the
story on that one so now that's coming
from today's
lecture the solution
X is what's the complete
solution it's just X particular right if
if if there is an if there is a solution
it's xal X particular there's nothing
you know there's just one solution if
there's one at all so it's Unique
solution unique means only
one unique solution if it
exists if it
exists in other words I would say let me
put it a different way they're either
zero or one
Solutions this is all in this case r
equal
n so I'm because many many applications
in reality The Columns will be uh will
will be what I'll later call
Independent
and we'll have uh nothing to look for in
the null space and we'll only have
particular Solutions
okay everybody see that
possibility but I need an example right
so let me create an
example what sort of a matrix what's the
shape of a matric that has full column
rank so can I squeeze in an example here
if it
exists let me put in an example and it's
just the right space to put in an
example because the example will be like
tall and thin it will
have well I mean here's an example 1 2
six 5 31 one one brilliant example okay
so there's a matrix
a and what's its
rank what's the rank of that
Matrix how many pivots will I find if I
do
elimination two right two I see a pivot
there I I've certainly those two columns
are headed off in different
directions when I do elimination I'll
certainly get another pivot here fine
and I can use those to clean out below
and above so the actually tell me what
it's row
reduced reduced row Echelon form would
be can you carry
that that elimination process to The
Bitter
End so what what does that mean I
subtract a multiple of this Row from
these rows so I clean up all zeros
there then I've got some pivot here what
do I do with that I go subtract it below
and above and then I divide through and
what's the what's R for that example
maybe I can you'll allow me to put that
just here in the next
board what's the row reduced Echelon
form just out of practice for that
matrix it's got ones in the pivots it's
got the identity Matrix a little 2x two
identity Matrix and below it all
zeros that's a matrix that really has
two independent rows and they're the
first two actually the first two rows
are independent they're not in the same
direction but the other rows are
combinations of the first two
so so uh is there always a solu solution
to ax equal B tell tell me what's the
picture here for this Matrix a this is a
case of full column rank the two columns
are give two
pivots there's nothing in the null space
there's no combination of those columns
that gives the zero column except the z0
combination so there's nothing in the
null space but is there always a
solution to a x equal B what's up with
ax equal
B I've got four four equations here and
only two
x's so the answer is certainly no
there's not always a solution if the so
I may have Zero Solutions and if I make
a random Choice I'll have Zero Solutions
or if I make a great particular choice
of the right hand side which just
happens to be a combination of those two
guys like tell me one right hand side
that would have a
solution tell me a right hand side that
would have a
solution well z00 z0 okay no prize for
that one uh tell me another one another
right hand side that has a solution
would be
4376 I could add the two
columns right what would be the total
complete solution if the right hand side
was
there would be the particular solution
one one one of that column plus one of
that and that would be the only
solution so there would be X particular
would be one one in the case when the
right side is the sum of those two
colums and that's it so that would be a
case with one
solution okay that's this is the typical
setup with full column rank now I go to
full row rank
you see the sort of natural symmetry of
this discussion full row
rank
means r equal
m so this is what I'm interested in now
r equal
m okay what's up with
that
um how many pivots
M
so what happens when we do elimination
in that
case I'm going to get M pivots so every
row has a pivot right every row has a
pivot then what about
solvability what about this business of
for which right hand sides can I solve
it so that's my question I can
solve ax equal B for which right hand
sides four you see what's
coming I do
elimination I don't get any zero rows so
there aren't any requirements on B I can
solve a equal B for every
B I can solve ax equal B for every right
hand side so this is the
existence exists a
solution now tell me so the so every row
has
a pivot in it so how many free variables
are there how many free variables in
this
case if I had n variables that to start
with how many are used up by pivot
variables R which is M so I'm left with
left
with n minus
r free
variables
okay so this case of full row
rank I can always solve and then this
tells me how many variables are free and
this is of course n minus M this is n
minus M free variables can I do an
example you know the best way for me to
do an example is just to transpose that
example
so let me take let me take that Matrix
that had column 1265 and make it a
row and let me take 3111 as the second
row and let me ask you this is my Matrix
a what's its
rank what's the rank of that Matrix
sorry to
ask but not sorry really because because
we're just getting the idea of rank
what's the rank of that
Matrix two exactly two there will be two
pivots what will the row reduce Echelon
form be anybody know that one actually
tell me not only you have to tell me not
only there be two pivots but which will
be the pivot columns which Columns of
this Matrix will be pivot columns so the
First Column is
fine and then I go on to the next column
and what do I get do I get a second
pivot out of will I get a second pivot
in this position yes so the pivots when
I get all the way to R will be
there and here will
be some numbers
I this is the part that I previously
called f this is the part that so the
the here the pivot columns in R will be
the identity Matrix there are no zero
rows no zero rows because the rank is
two but there' be stuff over
here and that will uh enter the special
Solutions and the null space okay so
this is a typical Matrix
with Ral M smaller than n now finally
I've got a space here for Ral m equal
n I'm off in the corner here with the
most important case of
all so what's up with this
Matrix so let me give an example okay
brilliant
example 1 12
31 tell me what how do I describe a
matrix that has rank r equal m equal n
so the Matrix is square right it's a
square Matrix and if I know its rank is
it's full rank now I don't have to say
full column rank or full row rank I just
say full rank because the count column
count and the row count are the same and
the rank is as big as it can be and what
kind of a matrix have I
got it's
invertible so that exactly the
invertible matrices Ral m equal N means
the and what's the row Echelon form the
the reduced row Echelon form for an
invertible Matrix for a square nice
Square invertible
matrix it's
I
right
so you you see that the the good
matrices are the ones that kind of come
out trivially in
R you reduce them all the way to the
identity Matrix what's the null space
for this for this Matrix can I just
hammer away with questions what's the
null space for this
Matrix the null space of that Matrix is
the zero Vector only the zero Vector
only what are the conditions to solve ax
equal B which right hand sides B are
okay if I want to solve ax equal B for
this example so I a is this B is B1
B2 what are the conditions on B1 B2 none
at all
right so this is the case this is the
case where I can solve so I'm coming
back here I can since the rank equals m
I can solve for every B
and since the rank is also n there's a
unique
solution let me summarize the whole
picture
here here's the whole picture I could
have r equal m equal n this is the case
where this is the identity
Matrix and this is the case where
there's one
solution that's the Square invertible
chapter 2
case now we're into chapter three we
could have r equal m smaller than
n now that's what we had over there and
the row Echelon form looked like the
identity with some zero
rows and that was the case where there
are zero or ones
solution to I'm when I say solution I
mean to axal
B so this case there's always one this
case there's zero or one and now let me
take the case of full column rank
but some
uh extra
rows so now our
has well the
identity I'm almost tempted to write the
identity Matrix and then F but that
isn't necessarily
right I have I have is that right am I
sorry am I am I getting this correct
here or oh I'm I'm not my God this is
the case R equals n The Columns The
Columns are are okay that's the case
that was on that board r equal n full
column rank now I want the case where m
is smaller than n and I've got extra
columns okay there we
go so this is now the case of
full row rank
and it looks like if except that I can't
be sure that the pivot columns are the
first columns so the I and the F the F
could be partly mixed into the
I can I can I write that with just like
that so the the the F could be sort of
partly into the eye if if if the first
columns weren't the pivot columns now
how many solutions in this
case there's always a
solution this is the existence case
there's always a solution we're not
getting any zero rows there are no zero
rows here so there's always either one
or infinitely many
solutions
okay actually I guess there's always an
infinite number because we always have
some null space to deal with then the
final case is where R is smaller than M
and smaller than
n okay now that's the case where R is
the identity with some free stuff but
with some zero rows too and that's the
case where there's either no solution
because we didn't get a zero equals z
for some bees
or infinitely many
solutions okay
do this board really summarizes the
lecture and this sentence summarizes the
lecture the rank tells you
everything about the number of
solutions that number the rank R tells
you all the information except the exact
entries in the solutions for that you go
to the Matrix okay good have a great
weekend and I'll see you on
Monday